Hey guys, this is going to be an
extensive video on back extensions. When
I say back extensions, really they
should probably be called hip
extensions, but that would kind of be
vague. Just out of tradition, it's
called back extensions. But I'm going to
explain why I don't like this name. But
here I've got a glute ham developer and
here I've got a 45 degree back raise or
45 degree
hyperun. Um, you can do them off either
one. With this, your legs are going to
be horizontal and your torso will go
from vertical to horizontal. And then
this, your legs are at a 45 degree
angle. What's the difference between the
two? I actually published a journal
article. It's called, "Are all hip
extension exercises created equal? I
have this linked onto my blog. Um, and I
have the the full article you can pull
up. The torque angle curves are
different um at the hip. If you don't
understand that, read the article. I
also filmed a video on it uh on YouTube
called Are All Hip Extension Exercise
Great Equals. So, if you're interested
in knowing how these exercises differ,
then you can pull it up. But in truth,
it's not going to make a big deal
whether you do the the horizontal
version or the 45 degree version.
They're both very good. They both both
activate the hamstrings and glutes
really well. Um I'm going to do most of
my demonstrations, actually probably all
of my demonstration off of this today.
So, starting off with body weight. All
right. You want to make sure that the
hip that this pad goes right underneath
like my pelvic bone is like even with
this pad here. So, this way I can go
down all the way. You want it as high as
you can go upwards without making you
round your low back. So, if I come to
the bottom, you can see that I can I'm
stretching my hamstrings maximally and
this pad does not interfere. it doesn't
make me round. Um, so that's the most
important thing is getting this right.
If you have it too far up to where
you're like this and there's a big gap,
then you don't feel it in the glutes as
much. You feel it more in the
hamstrings. So, you don't want a huge
gap here. And then if you have it too
low, like right here. And if I come down
to the bottom, I have to round. I'm
forced to. Now, actually, if you are
trying to work the erector
spine, then you should have it like
this. You should have the pad right up
here at the belly button and then hold
on to it like a weight and actually
round your round your back and then
extend your back. This way you'll be
focusing more on the spine
erectors. But that that's not how most
people don't do these with the intention
of working their erectors. They do these
with the intention working their glutes
and hamstrings. So I'm going to show you
how to work more glutes and hamstrings.
So setting up if you want to work more
glutes. If you look at my feet on this,
I can do a wide stance. Not every unit.
Let's see. This is a sumo base that I
got from Elite FTS. So, I can go wide
and flare my feet out. Most of them make
you go narrow, but you can still flare
your feet out. In one study, um, flaring
the feet out like this, uh, showed that
it activated sign, uh, like I think like
30 20 to 30% more glutes. So, flare your
feet. I flare my feet out at about a 45
degree angle. Some people flare them out
even more. So, you're putting the hips
in external rotation so the glutes can
fire harder. So, make sure you flare the
feet. Now, I'm going to come down. This
is how I teach body weight. There's kind
of three ways people do it. The first
way people will kind of go like this and
then they come up and they come up all
the way where they do hip extension and
spinal
extension. So, hip extension is bending
through here. spinal extensions bending
through the spine and they'll finish the
top like this. I don't like that because
um the glutes don't work as hard because
your back fatigues and the glutes and
hamstrings could do more. So, I don't
recommend doing it that way. The next
way is just to stay in neutral. So, down
here I have a neutral spine. Here I have
a neutral
spine. And this way is perfectly fine to
do and a lot of my clients do it this
way. And then the third way is to do
them with a rounded upper back and kind
of a posterior pelvic tilt at the top of
the movement. What this looks like is,
and this is the way I teach people who
can never feel their their glutes
working in a back extension. What I do
is I have them come to the bottom and
they're like this and I say, "Okay,
relax your upper back. Relax
everything." And they have a hard time
shutting it down. And I go and I make
them round your upper back. And then
they go like this. Okay, round. relax.
Round then they're relaxed and then I
make them actively round their upper
back like this. And then I say, imagine
there's a pin going through your hips
and you're just swiveing through that
pin. You're swiveing. You're making the
glutes pull to erect your torso. But
then at the top you have a big glute
squeeze. And I tell them, imagine
pushing your hips into the pad like
you're humping the pad.
And when you envision that and then
squeeze the glutes really hard, you will
actually posterior pelvic tilt. And
since posterior pelvic tilt is kind of
the same thing as hip extension in the
hip socket, so you won't be able to come
up quite as high. So what this looks
like is like this round and just go like
this, but I keep that rounded position.
This is the top right here. I can't go
anymore with my with my glutes. my hips
won't come up anymore because they're
posterior and
tilted. So, all of these different back
extensions can be used depending on the
goal. But with most of my people, I try
to kind of get them in between the last
two methods, in between neutral and like
a rounded upper back poster pelvic tilt.
So, you'll see my clients, they look
differently on these. Some of them do
them like this, like this. Some of them
round and do like
this. I've found that a lot of the more
advanced males, they feel the most in
their glutes when they round and they
just go like
this and it looks like they're not
coming up that high, but you have them
bust out like 20 reps like that and
their glutes are
screaming. Now, one thing I've been
examining is the effects of
load. Now, I can I'm really strong at
these. I can do like 100 lb and a band.
I've done 150 lbs for 15 reps
before, which I'll explain in a minute.
But I can get an amazing glute workout
just from body weight. So lately, I do
three sets of 20 with just body weight
with about 40 seconds of rest in between
set and I get this huge glute pump. So
your glutes don't know what load you're
using. All they respond to is how hard
they're working. you can make them work
really hard with just body weight if you
focus and use good
form. Um, one problem some people have
when their legs are straightened out
like this is their the back of their
knee hurts. When this happens, I will
actually adjust this pad to come up more
and make them have a little bit of knee
bend when they do it like this. So,
their knee their their leg will be bent.
Obviously, the pad would have to be up
higher and then that takes the knee pain
out of it. Most people can do it with
straight legs just fine. Okay. So, I
will do three sets of 20 just like
this. Three, four, five. Get to 20.
Glutes are burning. Hamstrings are
burning. Rest 40 seconds. Do it three
more times. Sometimes I can do three
sets of 25 and once I did three sets of
30 with 40 seconds rest. But that's a
great way to burn the glutes. My lighter
female clients can do like three sets of
30-ish and they feel their glutes a ton.
I've also done a set of 100. Um, but I
got really sore on the hamstrings the
next day. I don't like being really
sore, but you can you can work your way
up to where you're doing a ton of these.
But just make sure you focus the tension
on the glutes and hamstrings and don't
feel so much in the back. Now, there's
different ways to utilize resistance
here. The first way that I utilize
resistance, well, before I go
resistance, you can also just put your
hands in the prisoner position like
this. This makes it
harder. And I would say that raising
your arms up like this in the prisoner
position is probably equal to holding on
to like 20 to 30 lbs right here because
this is way up high along the lever
length. So, prisoner. And then you do
single leg with this. Take one leg out.
Okay, you can start off just like this.
But if you do prisoner, this is actually
a very hard exercise to do one leg at a
time. Do it with your weaker leg first.
Repeat with the stronger leg.
Okay. Now, holding on to weight here,
I've got 20 lbs. What people try to do
when they hold on the weight is they
will start here and then they get it
closer and closer to the hips. If you
have it directly under the hips, it's
not adding any resistance. So the higher
you hold it up, the more um torque it's
going to require out of the hips. So
what I do when I have people use lighter
dumbbells as I make them position it
under the chin just like
this. Then once the load gets heavier, I
have them hold it like this. Now I don't
want their elbows hitting here cuz then
they can't go down as deep. So I say
elbows out and they can go deep. Come
up. Always make sure that you go down
all the way and get a big stretch. Also,
when you're coming down, try to feel it
in the glutes
eentrically and then power it back
up. Okay. Now, I'm going to show you how
to do it with
chains. With a
chain, just wrap it around your neck.
And then I hold it like right here.
This is good because
again it's high up high up along the
neck. So it's a long lever. I've done
like five chains before. I think they're
like 11 lbs each. So like 55 lbs and
that's gives me a pretty good workout
because it's long up the
lever. Um but when I hold on when I use
dumbbells I can use 100 lbs easy and I
can get 30 reps this way.
So, most of my stronger guys can do the
100 pounders and most of my strongest my
stronger women can do like 70 pounders,
70s and 80s, but they have a hard time
holding it. Eventually, they reach a
point where their hip extensors could do
more, but their arms fatigue. But the
the heavy dumbbell looks like
this. Hold it close. Try and get it
close to the chin and not down here. And
then just
Just like
that. And now I'm going to show you
band. So, you can only do bands when you
have a special unit. This Elite FTS has
band pegs. I think
uh Sorex makes them with band pegs as
well. When I teach women the bands, I
just use So, I loop these around like
this, but I'll just use one of these,
just like this. and then it gets
stretched. And this is very hard. It's
very hard for women to do the
bands. Um, actually I teach men this way
as well, but eventually once the men get
strong enough, I use both bands at the
same time. And actually, um, what I'll
do is I'll put a towel at the back of
their neck because it kind of can
aggravate the neck. In fact, I'll show
that. Get a here.
So what I do here is I go like
this and I will wrap this in a towel
just like this and then I will come over
like this. Hold it here. This is pretty
tough.
What I found with the bands is that even
if you're trying to take the erectors
out of it and use mostly glutes and
hamstrings, you do feel in your erectors
a lot. So if you're trying to use the
erectors and really work them, these
bands are awesome. There's almost no way
to do them without feeling them a lot in
the spine of erectors, which is good.
who needs a strong back. But
uh you can also do bands and dumbbells
at the same time. And this is for like
very advanced people. So the most
advanced people you
can, you know,
combine bands and
dumbbell. So it's like
this. Like that.
Okay.
Again, if I'm trying to work the glutes
and I already did heavy squats or heavy
deadlifts or heavy hip thrusts, I
already got that heavy stimulus out of
the way. Now, I'm going to the back
extension. I want to get the high reps
in. I want to get metabolic stress. So,
most of the time I do this with just
body weight. Again, three sets of 20 to
30 reps with 40 seconds rest in between
sets. But then sometimes I do them heavy
and I want to work more glutes and
hamstrings and then I'll do them with
dumbbells or with bands or with band and
dumbbell. Um
so
again there's different ways to do this
depending on your goal. You can load
them up a lot of different ways. You can
do one leg, two leg, hands in the
prisoner position. Uh hands folded in
the mummy position.
chain band, dumbbell under the chin,
dumbbell like this, and then
combinations
thereof. But it's very important that
you learn how to feel these more in in
your glutes. You'll always feel them in
the hamstrings, but you want to be able
to feel them in the glutes as well. Some
people have a really hard time feeling
in the glutes. So again, I'll review the
tips. Flare the feet out. Externally
rotate the hips. round the upper back
and then just kind of feel the glutes
pulling you up. Squeeze them. Posterior
pelvic tilt. Pelvic tilt this way. Kind
of like you're trying to draw your your
pelvic bone toward towards your rib
cage. Okay? And then push your hips into
the pad just like this. So when you do
this, right, if you were looking from
the side view, I can see this stretch
mark like stretching up here to show
that the glutes are contracting right
here. When I watch people if they have
like tighter like yoga pants on for my
women or like males have like say
tighter fitting shorts, you can see
right here these lines up here to show
that the glutes are contracting. But you
want a strong glute contraction at the
very top. And once you get good at it,
you can just it's like you're feeling
the glutes just squeezing together
um raising your torso.
So, horizontal back extensions, 45°,
tons of different variations,
but try the three sets for high reps
method for glutes with low rest time. I
really think you you'll like it. It's
great for metabolic stress. This is a
staple in my gym. All my clients are
doing it. And my better female clients,
they like this. They feel their glutes
burning with this just as much as they
do with the the band hip thrust. So,
give it a try. See if you like it.